Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Steelworkers of America PE.011
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Steelworkers of America
1935-1997
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.011
3.5 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons and 1 shared manuscript box
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Steelworkers of America (1935-1997) is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. The United Steelworkers of America was founded in 1942 and through mergers with other unions has become one of largest industrial unions in North America. Ranging in date from the 1940s through the 1990s, the collection consists primarily of agreements, contracts and constitutions, as well as printed ephemera such as fliers, brochures, newspaper clippings, pamphlets and other publications. The material in the collection was generated by the national and international bodies of the United Steelworkers of America, various Districts and Locals, as well as rank and file committees.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series. Folders are arranged alphabetically within series. The series arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I: National Union Files, 1935-1997
Series II: District and Local Files, 1945-1986
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Steelworkers of America (1935-1997) consists of agreements, contracts, and constitutions, as well as printed ephemera such as fliers, brochures, newspaper clippings, pamphlets and other publications. There are several publications related to the National War Labor Board (1944) as well as publications relating to national wage stabilization and wage policy in the steel industry, dating from the late 1940s through the 1950s. In addition to material generated by the national and international bodies of the United Steelworkers of America, the collection also contains constitutions, fliers, and publications from various districts, locals, and rank and file committees.
Historical Note
In 1936, John L. Lewis, president of the United Mine Workers of America, named Philip Murray chairman of the Steel Workers Organizing Committee (SWOC). The Committee was charged with leading an organizing drive of the entire steel industry. Out of the SWOC, the United Steelworkers of America was formed, holding its founding convention in 1942. Murray was elected as the first president and served until his death in 1952. Since its founding, various unions have merged with the United Steelworkers, most recently, in 2005, the Paper, Allied-Industrial, Chemical and Energy Workers (PACE) International Union. This merger created the largest industrial union in North America, a union not only of steelworkers but also workers in industries such as manufacturing, health care, pharmaceuticals, mining, energy and utilities. As of 2009, the United Steelworkers of American had over 850,000 active members in the United States, Canada, and the Caribbean.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. There is no accession record associated with this collection.
In 2025, materials from accession 2019.056, which is associated with Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Subjects (PE 029), were transferred to this collection.
Brochures.; Circular letters.; Printed ephemera.; Labor -- United States.; Fliers (printed matter); Agreements.; Constitutions.; Clippings (information artifacts); Contracts; Labor unions; Publications (documents); Pamphlets.; United Steelworkers of America
- Series I: National Union Files, 1935-1997; 3.5 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons and 1 shared manuscript box
  - Agreements and Contracts, 1947-1956 (Box 1)
  - Agreements and Contracts: United States Steel Corporation, 1956-1960 (Box 1)
  - Agreements and Contracts: United States Steel Corporation, 1971-1980 (Box 1)
  - Audit Reports, 1942-1974 (Box 1)
  - Bethlehem Steel Corporation, 1952-1977 (Box 1)
  - By-Laws for Local Unions, 1970, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters, 1949-1963, undated (Box 1)
  - Committee on Civil Rights, 1954-circa 1972, undated (Box 1)
  - Committee on Civil Rights, circa 1974, undated (Box 1)
  - Constitutional Convention, 1952-1958 (Box 1)
  - Constitutional Convention, 1960-1984 (Box 1)
  - Constitutions, 1944-1980 (Box 1)
  - Education Department, 1954-1986, undated (Box 1)
  - Education Department: Action Guide, undated (Box 1)
  - Education Department: Civil Rights Kit, 1969-1972, undated (Box 1)
  - Education Department: Taxes Kit Material, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Elections Manual, 1968, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Fliers, Brochures and Ephemera, 1945-1960, 1980-1990, undated (Box 2)
  - International Safety and Health Department, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Labor Institute (Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ), 1953 (Box 2)
  - Legislative Department, 1978, 1997 (Box 2)
  - National Conference on Human Rights, 1958 (Box 2)
  - National Training Fund, undated (Box 2)
  - National War Labor Board, undated (Box 2)
  - National War Labor Board (I), 1944 (Box 2)
  - National War Labor Board (II), 1944 (Box 2)
  - New Members Department, 1970, undated (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Articles and Publications Relating to, 1935-1996 (Box 2)
  - Pension Plan, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets and Publications (un-numbered), 1942-1956, undated (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets and Publications (un-numbered), 1958, 1964, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets and Publications (#100-199), circa 1950s-1980s, undated (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets and Publications (#200-302), circa 1950s-1980s, undated (Box 2)
  - Press Releases, 1942, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Public Relations Department, 1959, undated (Box 2)
  - Publicity and Education Department, undated (Box 2)
  - Rank and File, 1973-1976 (Box 2, Box Shared Tamiment 190, Folder 11)
  - Ravenswood Lockout (Ravenswood Aluminum Corporation), 1990-1992 (Box 2)
  - Research Department, 1945-1956 (Box 2)
  - Research Department, 1956-1959 (Box 2)
  - Sadlowski, Edward, 1976-1977, 1981, undated (Box 2)
  - Serial Publications (Newsletters and Special Editions), 1960-1970 (Box 2)
  - Statements, Speeches and Addresses, 1952-1959 (Box 3)
  - Steel Companies: Publications by, 1959-1962 (Box 3)
  - Union Label Sample Kit, undated (Box 3)
  - Wage Policy and Steel Prices: Reports and Statements, 1949-1957 (Box 3)
  - Wage Stabilization Board (I), 1951-1952, undated (Box 3)
  - Wage Stabilization Board (II), 1951-1952, undated (Box 3)
- Series II: District and Local Files, 1945-1986; 1 linear foot in 1 record carton
  - District 4, 1986 (Box 3)
  - District 31, 1969-1979 (Box 3)
  - District 50, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Local 65 (Chicago, IL), 1945 (Box 3)
  - Local 169 (Mansfield, OH), 1952 (Box 3)
  - Local 302, circa 1948 (Box 3)
  - Local 616 (Morenci Miners' Union, Clifton, AZ), 1984 (Box 3)
  - Local 890 (Bayard, NM), 1975 (Box 3)
  - Local 1010 (East Chicago, IN), 1977 (Box 3)
  - Local 1630 (Depew, NY), 1975 (Box 3)
  - Local 2266, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Local 3701, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Local 5000 (Chicago, IL), 1956 (Box 3)
  - Local 5030, 1959 (Box 3)
  - Local 5227 (Reading, PA), 1976 (Box 3)
  - Local 7528 (Bridgeport, CT), 1979 (Box 3)
  - Local 8571 (Boston, MA), 1980-1983 (Box 3)